A Guide to the International Union of Women Architects (UIFA) Conference Materials, 1981-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
International Union of Women Architects (UIFA) Conference Materials, 1981-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2012-001
4.0 cu. ft. 3 boxes, 4 oversize folders
The International Union of Women Architects (UIFA) was founded in 1963 by Solange d'Herbez de la Tour. The organization aims to promote women in the profession by increasing the public's awareness of contributions made to the field by women and by creating a network of international colleagues. UIFA encourages the exchange of information through its regular conferences hosted by participating chapters from around the globe.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials are compiled from donations between 2001-2007.
Historical Note
Founded in 1963, by Solange d'Herbez de la Tour, the International Union of Women Architects/Union International des Femmes Architectes (UIFA) aims to make known and promote the Woman Architect; to establish relationships and exchanges between professional women; to collect all information concerning the stature and professional life of these women world-wide; to favor friendship links and solidarity, between all members, without political, racial, or religious discrimination. UIFA also works closely with the International Union of Architects (UIA) and others for the interest of the built environment.
UIFA members range from over 75 different countries.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications and presentation material from UIFA international events beginning with the Second Workshop of UIFA in 1981 and continuing to present day conferences. Newsletters and pamphlets from individual chapters of representing nations (specifically UIFA Japan) are also present.
A significant portion of these materials have been donated by Milka Bliznakov, International Archives of Women in Architecture (IAWA) founder as well as frequent speaker and attendee at UIFA events. Bliznakov used UIFA Congresses as a catalyst for meeting leading woman in the profession and for encouraging participants to donate collections to the IAWA.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
See also Kristen K. Fallon Ms2000-035, Gertrude Galster Ms1996-020, L. Jane Hastings Ms2004-004, Gerda Pingel, Berta Rahm Ms1998-011, Jean Linden Young Ms1998-022, and Ute Westrom Ms1996-023 for additional UIFA materials and information.
Index Terms
Persons:
Gorgenyi, Judit; Hazwaw, Masako; Higashi, Yumiko; Hoksza, Eva; Inagaki, Hiroko; Ishikawa, Yaeko; Katsumi, Noriko; Masamune, Kazuko; Matsukawa-Tsuchida, Junko; Møller, Alice Finnerup; Nanasy, Ilona; Nanay, Eva; Oron, Joyce, 1954-; Suzuki, Hisako; Tihanyi, Judit; Toshiko-Yamamoto, Kimiyo; Xu, Yifang; Yakabe, Masako
Corporate Names:
International Union of Women Architects.
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women-owned architectural firms.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- International UIFA Events
  - UIFA pamphlet and Congress Calendar, undated (Box 1)
  - Second Workshop of UIFA, Berlin, Germany conference materials, May 12-13, 1981 (Box 1)
  - 6th Congress UIFA, Paris, France conference materials, April 27-30, 1983 (Box 1)
  - 7th Congress UIFA, Berlin, Germany conference materials, October 10-12, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 9th Congress UIFA, Copenhagen, Denmark conference materials, August 19-22, 1991
    - General information (Box 1)
    - Poster, Diwan of H. H. the Ruler in Dubai (Oversize Folder 1)
  - 10th Congress UIFA, Cape Town, South Africa conference materials, March 12-19, 1993 (Box 1)
  - 11th Congress UIFA, Budapest, Hungary conference materials, September 2-8, 1996 (Box 1)
  - 12th Congress UIFA, Tokyo, Japan conference materials, September 1-7, 1998 (Box 1)
  - 13th Congress UIFA, Vienna Austria conference materials, June 30, 2001
    - General information (Box 1)
    - Poster, Junko Matsukawa-Tsuchida: "Renewal of 'New Towns' in the midst of population aging" (Oversize Folder 2)
    - Poster, Kazuko Masamune: "An 88 year old women's house - a project for quadruple families" (Oversize Folder 2)
    - Poster, Kimiyo Toshiko Yamamoto: "The Second Life" (Oversize Folder 2)
    - Poster, Yaeko Ishikawa: "A New Style of Housing for the Elderly" (Oversize Folder 2)
    - Poster, Yumiko Osawa Higashi: "Houses for Three Generations" (Oversize Folder 2)
  - 14th Congress UIFA, Toulouse France conference material, September 1-6, 2003
    - General information (Box 1)
    - Poster, Alice Finnerup Moller: "Improving the architecture and the environment in a housing complex" (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, Hiroko Inagaki: "Desiccant cooling system of air typr solar houses using silica gel" (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, Joyce Oron: "Modi'in Natural Reserve and Mode-Bothelo Wizo Center" (Box 3)
    - Poster, Junko Matsukawa-Tsuchida design for "Suzakake (Gender Equality Center at Sumido Ward)" (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, Kazuko Masamune: "Strike the balance between 'paid' and 'unpaid' work of men and women - from the viewpoint of the design of [a] kitchen with a little ingenuity" (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, UIFA Japan newsletters (Oversize Folder 4)
    - Poster, Union of Women Architects of Belgium (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, Yaeko Ishikawa: "Investigation of methods of assisted living for senile residents in public senior housing" (Oversize Folder 3)
    - Poster, Yifang Xu: "Space regressed to citizen: the project planning for Wuxian guan" (Oversize Folder 3)
  - 15th Congress UIFA, Bucharest, Romania conference materials, October 1-7, 2007
    - General information (Box 1)
    - Poster, Judit Gorgenyi: Ecole secondaire lutherane and Bank Creditanstal Rt Salle de conseil - Hungary (Box 2)
    - Poster, Eva Hoksza: Kecskemet - Hungary (Box 2)
    - Poster, Eva Nanay: Park d'habitation - Budapest, Hungary (Box 2)
    - Poster, Ilona Nanasy: Subcenter of District Building - Budapest, Hungary (Box 2)
    - Poster, Judit Tihanyi and Gyorgy Halmos: Ecumenical Protestant Church, Erdokertes - Hungary (Box 2)
- UIFA Chapters
  - UIFA Japan (Box 1)
    Scope and Content
    The UIFA Japan Chapter (also known as UIFA JAPON) materials contain a collection of chapter newsletters from 2003-2006. Also present are publications, correspondence with UIFA Japan president Yumiko Higashi, photographs, and exhibition materials from "Houses for Working Women," February 2006.
    - 10th Anniversary Presentation, [see also 14th Congress], 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 2004-2006 (Box 1)
    - Exhibit Materials "Houses for Working Women," January 13, 2006-February 12, 2006 (Box 1, Box 2)
      The exhibition "Houses for Working Women" was presented by the Women Architects and Engineers Association and held in Tokyo from 13 January - 12 February 2006. Exhibitors present in collection include: Noriko Katsumi "How to live in winter weather" and "House with business space;" Masako Yakabe "House for living with grown children" and "House with mother's quarter;" Yumiko Higashi "Ultra-small house" and "Home with a classroom;" Sohu "Small home office;" Hisako Suzuki "Working couple house," "Two generations house with two independent buildings," and "House for three generations;" Masako Hazawa "House using a very small lot" and House with built in furniture."
    - Exhibit Catalog, "For the Future: The Pioneering Women in Architecture, 2013 (Box 2)
      In late 2010, the International Archive of Women in Architecture partnered with UIFA JAPON to develop a traveling exhibit entitled "For the Future: The Pioneering Women in Architecture." The exhibit, conceived as a celebration of the 25th anniversary of the IAWA, featured pioneering architects from Japan and the United States. The exhibit was expanded to memorialized IAWA founder Dr. Milka T. Bliznakov, who passed away in November 2010. Installation of the exhibit was delayed by the Great East Japan earthquake (Friday 11 March 2011). UIFA JAPON members collaborated with the IAWA to display the exhibition at eight venues across the Kanto region of Japan from June 2011 through March 2013. The catalog is printed in Japanese and English.
    - Japanese Center for Advancement of Working Women, Publication, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters, 2003-2006 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 1)